Well, it's the 1840s now and that North
South sectional conflict is heating all
the way up now. And that's because
immigrants were showing up in record
numbers and the debate about slavery was
making everyone more than a little
cranky. So, I reckon we ought to talk
about it. And if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay. Now, the debate over the expansion
of slavery tends to suck up all the
oxygen in the room during this period.
And that's fair since, you know, it did
ultimately lead to a civil stinking war.
But there was another development trying
to suck in some of the oxygen in the
1840s and50s, namely a massive wave of
immigrants arriving to the American
shores. And that's going to cause its
own set of problems. So in this period,
millions of European immigrants arrived
in the United States, the majority of
which were Irish and German. Now, most
of the Irish who came during this period
were Catholics and had been forced to
migrate on account of the Irish potato
famine, which had caused mass starvation
and hardship for many lower-ass Irish.
And so they decided that the United
States would be their land of
opportunity. And they sailed their hind
parts right on over. And in general,
where the Irish landed, the Irish
stayed. And in their case, that meant
the large industrial cities in the
north. And there many of them found work
in low-wage factory jobs. And without a
doubt, the abundance of low-wage
industrial workers fueled the market
revolution and contributed mightily to
American prosperity. Additionally, many
of these Irish immigrants formed ethnic
enclaves in their home cities, which is
to say they kept their cultural
traditions alive, including Catholic
worship and in some cases speaking the
native Irish language. Oh, and by the
way, if you want Nokai to follow along
with this video and all my videos, check
the link in the description. Anyway, the
other group that immigrated in huge
numbers during this period were Germans.
And for the most part, they left Germany
on account of economic hardship and the
political instability caused by the
failed revolution of 1848 that sought
democratic reforms. Now, the German
immigrants behaved a little differently
than their Irish counterparts. And no
small reason for that is because German
immigrants tended to have a little more
boom boom than the Irish poor. And so
with that extra wealth, German
immigrants more often migrated westward
into the interior of the United States
where they established farms and
homesteads. But like the Irish, Germans
also form communities where they upheld
their cultural traditions, like
establishing Catholic or Lutheran
churches and spreen with each other.
However, I should mention that some
Germans migrated to industrial cities
and formed their own communities as
well. For example, in New York, German
immigrants established an ethnic enclave
known as Klein Deutsland, or if you're
sassy, Little Germany. And here they
established German theaters and churches
and synagogues, not to mention German
schools known as, wait for it,
kindergarten. So, you know, if you're
ever in kindergarten yourself, then, you
know, go hug a German. So, that's great.
Millions of Irish and German immigrants
are flooding the American population and
contributing a significant amount of
vital work that helped the American
economy thrive during this period. So,
I'm sure that native-born Americans saw
that contribution and just went door to
door and gave these immigrants a nice
warm hug. Right? I mean, [laughter]
right? Well, you probably know that no
such hugs of gratitude were given, but
instead what we got was a significant
nivist backlash in the face of all this
immigration. Now, nativeism refers to a
movement to protect the interests of
native-born citizens against the
influence and encroachment of foreign
interests and cultures. Now, nativeism
had been a constant reality in the first
few decades of the 19th century, but by
1854, America's political party system
was in a crisis due to the growing
sectional tension over slavery. And out
of the political chaos of that moment, a
new political party was born, built
entirely on a foundation of nivist
policies, namely the Nothing Party. Now,
the real name for the organization was
the American Party, but they quickly
became known as the Nothing since the
party had developed out of a secretive
nivist organization. And apparently, if
someone asked a member whether the
organization existed, the member's
response was always to be, "I know
nothing." But the name is kind of a
misnomer because the Nothings did at
least know one thing, namely that they
hated Irish Catholics and they built
their party platform on the foundation
of that hatred. Like these nivists
really believe that Irish Catholics were
some kind of secret agent sent to
America by the Pope in order to
undermine civic institutions like
schools and pollute the gene pool with
their filthy Irish DNA. And you're like,
"Wait a minute. Weren't the Irish
immigrants white?" Well, not by the
reckoning of these American nivists. The
Irish weren't white. They were Irish.
And this reality, like so many others
during this time, is intimately
connected to the market revolution and
expansion of democracy that we talked
about in the last unit. For example,
many of these Irish immigrants had
joined labor unions and got deeply
involved in local politics. And so,
nivists felt that immigrants were
corrupting elections and gaining way too
much influence in politics. Anyway, for
a few years, the Nothings rode a wave of
popularity and their candidates won a
significant number of state elections,
including representatives to state
legislatores and governors and mayors.
Now, they eventually died out and got
absorbed by the Republican party on
which more in a moment. So yeah, the
immigration thing was a big deal and
all, but by the 1850s, the sectional
debate over the expansion of slavery
grew louder and louder until it was all
that any American could really hear.
Now, remember what we talked about in
the last several videos, namely that
with the US acquiring so much territory
in the West, it created the occasion for
bitter fights regarding the expansion of
slavery into those lands. And that
debate essentially had three factions at
war with one another. The first faction
was made up of the free soil movement,
and they opposed the expansion of
slavery on economic grounds. In other
words, free soilers were not really
concerned about the moral question
slavery posed. Instead, they were
concerned that the westward expansion of
slavery would hinder the westward
expansion of free wage labor. Now, I've
established ad nauseium in previous
videos that the fundamental economic
nature of the north and south were very
different. The south was primarily
agricultural and relied for its wealth
and the work of millions of enslaved
black people. And then the north was
primarily industrial and focused on
manufacturing. And as such, its workers
were not enslaved but instead worked for
wages. And so the free soil ideology
argued that the slave power of the south
represented an existential threat to
free labor in the north. Additionally,
this ideology framed the north as the
bastion of progress and freedom since a
worker could theoretically start at the
bottom and work his way up to better
pay, more responsibility, and higher
social status. Slavery, on the other
hand, was a backwards institution
characterized by enslaved blacks and
poor whites who had no hope of
advancement. Therefore, free soilers
wanted to prevent slavery from expanding
into the western territory so that free
labor could have room to grow and
flourish. And to be clear, free soil
advocates did not so much oppose the
institution of slavery itself, but they
opposed the expansion of slavery into
new territories. Like they were
perfectly happy to allow slavery to
remain in the places where it was
already established. But southerners
could not agree to such terms because
without the expansion of slavery, free
states would quickly outnumber slave
states and suffocate the existence of
the very labor system on which they all
depended. Okay. Now, the second major
faction in the debate was the
abolitionist movement in the north that
wanted to prevent the expansion of
slavery because it was immoral. And it
wasn't just the expansion of slavery
they opposed. No, abolitionists, unlike
the free soilers, wanted to eradicate
the institution even where it already
existed. And in truth, this faction was
certainly a minority in the debate. But
as it turned out, they very much knew
how to make themselves heard. And they
used three distinct tactics to that end.
First, abolitionists presented moral
arguments against slavery. For example,
you had Martin Delaney, a free black man
from Virginia who was among the first
blacks admitted to Harvard Medical
School. But a large group of white
students there got their feelings hurt
that they were forced to learn alongside
black folks. And so they protested and
Delaney was expelled. That experience
convinced Delany that black people had
no future in the United States.
Therefore, he began supporting the
efforts of the American Colonization
Society, whose goal was to relocate
black Americans to a colony in Africa,
namely Liberia. But then Delaney
actually visited Liberia and changed his
mind about that and instead began to
denounce the effort to ship all of
America's black people to Africa. And so
he partnered with Frederick Douglas to
write for the abolitionist newspaper,
The North Star, and wrote tracks railing
against the injustice of colonization.
Black Americans, he argued, were
Americans first and not Africans.
Therefore, they should be able to secure
equal rights to white Americans in the
land of their birth. And then probably
the most potent example of abolitionist
presenting their moral arguments was the
publication of Uncle Tom's Cabin. So in
1852, Harriet Beecher Stowe published
this novel whose plot follows the escape
of an enslaved woman named Eliza who
attempts to carry her daughter to
freedom. And as the story unfolds over
hundreds of pages, Stowe takes great
pains to depict slavery as abusive and
brutal and fundamentally evil. And this
novel became the best-selling book in
the 19th century, second only to the
dang Bible. And even though it was
fiction, its depiction of the evils of
enslavement played an outsized role in
northern abolitionist effort to
eradicate slavery from the south. Now,
it probably goes without saying that
southern people were disgusted at the
popularity of this book because it
convinced a whole generation of
northerners that southerners were wicked
brutes on account of slavery. And so
they clutched their pearls and said,
"How dare you?" and then banned the book
and responded with their own novel and
set the record straight. It was called
Aunt Phyllis's Cabin written by Mary
Eastman. And in this story, slavery was
portrayed as a bright and happy reality
where benevolent masters oversaw pliant
and contented slaves. In fact, by
Eastman's reckoning, all the enslaved
people in the south just walked around
thanking the good lord that they had
such happy lives compared to all those
wage slaves in the north. Now, this book
was by far the bestselling novel in the
anti-T genre, but its numbers and
influence still pale in comparison with
Uncle Tom's Cabin. Okay. Now, the second
tactic used by some abolitionists was to
assist in the escape of the enslaved. So
in defiance of the fugitive slave law
included in the compromise of 1850, many
abolitionists refused to turn in
enslaved people who had escaped to the
north and some even helped create
systems that encouraged escape. Now the
most famous of these systems was known
as the Underground Railroad which wasn't
an actual railroad but just a metaphor
for the journey of escape which was made
up of a network of safe houseses and
conductors who led escapees to safety.
Anyway, the most successful and famous
of the conductors on the railroad was
Harriet Tubman who had herself escaped
slavery in 1849. And after the passage
of the fugitive slave law, Tubman
unlocked her boss mode and made 19 trips
to the south and liberated around 70
enslaved people by ushering them into
the northern states and into British
Canada as well. And then the third
tactic abolitionists used was good
old-fashioned violence. And there's no
more consequential example here than
John Brown's raid on Harper's Ferry. So
John Brown was a militant abolitionist
who had participated in the violent
conflict that erupted in Kansas over
whether it would become a slave or free
state. And I'll tell you that juicy
story in the next video. Anyway, Brown
was convinced that those soft
abolitionists like William Lloyd
Garrison who argue that slavery must be
abolished by means of moral persuasion
were utterly naive. Instead, Brown
agreed with abolitionists like Henry
Highland Garnet who declared that in the
history of the world, no enslaved or
oppressed people had ever gained their
freedom without violence. So, in order
to shut theist pie holes of Garrison and
his crew in 1859, Brown led a handful of
abolitionists to raid the federal
arsenal in Harper's Ferry, Virginia. and
his goal was to get all the weapons in
the arsenal and arm Virginia's enslaved
people in order to set off a slave
rebellion akin to the Haitian
Revolution. But that's not what
happened. No, the Virginia militia
quickly defeated Brown and his rebels
and put an end to the whole affair. They
captured Brown alive and publicly
executed him, but in doing so made a
martyr out of him that further inflamed
the tension between the North and the
South. And it was this event that played
a significant part in creating the
permanent division between the North and
the South. Since by southerners
reckoning, northern abolitionists proved
that they would be willing to use
violence to strip them of their
constitutional right to own enslaved
people. Okay. And finally, let me tell
you about the third side in the debate
over slavery, namely the idea that
slavery was a positive good. Now, this
position was most clearly articulated by
John C. Calhoun. And he argued that
enslavers of the past who considered
slavery to be a necessary evil were
absolutely wrong. In fact, those chumps
needed to get their big boy pants on and
realize that every ingredient that goes
into the slavery stew is altogether
sweet smelling and delicious. And
Calhoun had two major pieces of evidence
to support his argument. First, the idea
of white supremacy taught that members
of the white race, regardless of wealth
or status or education, were
fundamentally superior to members of the
black race. And therefore, since the
white folks were superior, then slavery
was a gift to the enslaved blacks
because they were not capable of
governing or protecting themselves.
While perhaps even more potent, Calhoun
supported his view of slavery by
constitutional arguments. So, southern
leaders pointed out that whatever moral
objections the framers of the
Constitution had about slavery, the
document itself protects the institution
since it didn't ban slavery, and it even
included portions like the three-fifths
clause, which furthered the interests of
slave states. Additionally, southerners
began to articulate a clear position on
states rights against federal intrusion.
For example, the 10th Amendment
guarantees that any power not explicitly
granted by the Constitution to the
federal government is reserved for the
states. Therefore, they argued since the
Constitution nowhere gives the federal
government the right to curtail slavery,
the power to abolish or protect slavery
remains squarely in the hands of each
state. Well, okay. You can click here to
watch my other videos for unit 5, or you
can click here to grab my video note
guides, which are going to help you get
all the contents of this course firmly
crammed into your brain folds. I'm glad
you came around, and I'll catch on the
flip-flop. I'm Lur.